Guide to the Gerhard and Hella Adler Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Gerhard and Hella Adler papers
1873-1959
1908-1956
GEN MSS 901
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5.04
(11 boxes)
The collection consists of material documenting aspects of the life and work of the Jungian analysts Gerhard Adler and Hella Adler. Material includes drawings, sketchbooks, diagnostic and other notes, handwriting samples, correspondence, and other material. Included are numerous oil, gouache, watercolor, chalk, and pencil "dream drawings," and drawings and sketches in books, on loose sheets, oil boards, and card scrolls.
Adler, Gerhard, 1904-1988
Adler, Hella
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Maggs Brothers Ltd.on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2011.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Gerhard Adler and Hella Adler
Gerhard Adler (1904-1989) and Hella Adler (1907-2009), husband and wife, Jungian analysts who helped found the Society of Analytical Psychology in 1945 and the Association of Jungian Analysts in 1977.
Gerhard was born in Berlin in 1904, studied under the psychologist Carl Jung in Zurich, and worked as an analyst and held a post in a child guidance clinic in England. His published works include: The Living Symbol: A Case Study in the Process of Individuation (1961), Studies in Analytical Psychology (1966), and Dynamics of the Self (1979). He co-edited the English translation of Jung's collected works (1953) and edited two volumes of Jung's correspondence (1973, 1984).
Hella was born in Berlin in 1907 and worked with Emma Jung in Zurich. Gerhard and Hella immigrated to England in 1936 to avoid Nazi persecution, and had two children, Michael (born in 1939) and Miriam (born in 1944). After the war, they lived in Hampstead, bringing up their family and seeing patients. Gerhard died in 1989, and Hella died in 2009.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of material documenting aspects of the life and work of the Jungian analysts Gerhard Adler and Hella Adler. Material includes drawings, sketchbooks, diagnostic and other notes, handwriting samples, correspondence, and other material. Included are numerous oil, gouache, watercolor, chalk, and pencil "dream drawings," and drawings and sketches in books, on loose sheets, oil boards, and card scrolls.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Correspondence, Notes, and Other Papers, 1873-1959. II. Drawings and Artwork, 1951-1956, undated.
Dream interpretation; Graphology; Psychoanalysis; Psychoanalysts; Jungian psychology; Drawings (visual works); Sketchbooks; Psychoanalysts; Adler, Gerhard, 1904-1988; Adler, Hella
- Correspondence, Notes, and Other Papers, 1873-1959; Series I; 2; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by format.
  - Account book, [1936] (Box 1)
  - Appointment calendars, 1948-1950; 3 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Adler, Gerhard, [circa 1920-1954] (Box 1)
    - Adler, Hella, [circa 1939-1941] (Box 1)
    - Börnstein, Walter, [circa 1908-1935] (Box 1)
    - Walter, Fritz, 1917-1920, undated (Box 1)
    - Unsorted, 1873-1953, undated; 5 (Box 1)
  - Diagnostic notes, 1952, undated; 7 (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Handwriting samples (adults), 1930s, undated; 5 (Box 1)
  - Handwriting samples (children), undated (Box 2)
  - Notes, 1945-1956, undated; 19 (Box 2)
  - Photographs, 1939, undated (Box 2)
  - Printed material, 1912-1951 (Box 2)
  - Statistics, undated (Box 2)
  - Stationery Hella Adler, undated (Box 2)
  - Unidentified writings, 1941-1952, undated; 4 (Box 2)
- Drawings and Artwork, 1951-1956, undated; Series II; 3.04; (9 boxes)
  Grouped by format or genre.
  - Sketchbooks, 1951-1953, undated; 14 (Box 2)
  - Sketchbooks (continued), undated; 2 (Box 3)
  - Drawings, 1952-1956; 2 (Box 3)
  - Watercolor paintings, undated (Box 3)
  - Clay sculpture, undated (Box 4)
  - Drawings and paintings, 1951-1953; 14 (Box 5 (Oversize))
  - Drawings and paintings (continued), 1951-1953; 4 (Box 6)
  - Rolled artwork, 1953-1954, undated; (10 rolls) (Box 7 (Oversize))
  - Rolled artwork, 1954, undated; (11 rolls) (Box 8 (Oversize))
  - Rolled artwork, 1953-1954, undated; (10 rolls) (Box 9 (Oversize))
  - Rolled artwork, 1953-1956, undated; (9 rolls) (Box 10 (Oversize))
  - Oil paintings, undated; 4 (Box 11 (Oversize))